Inventory of the I͡Uriĭ Il'ich Lodyzhenskiĭ papers
Hoover Institution Archives
I͡Uriĭ Il'ich Lodyzhenskiĭ papers
1921-1968
75072
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box, 3 microfilm reels (0.7 linear feet)
Memoirs, other writings, bulletins, reports, and printed matter relating to medical practice in Russia during World War I, the Russian Revolution and Civil War, efforts to resettle White Russian veterans and refugees after the war, and activities of the International Anticommunist Entente.
Lodyzhenskiĭ, I͡Uriĭ Ilʹich.
Location of Original Materials
In part, originals in Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual or digital material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1975.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1888 Born, Zubtsovskii uezd, Tverskaia guberniia, Russia
1912-1914 Doctor, St. Petersburg Orthopedic Institute
1914-1915 Chief medical officer, Caucasian Cavalry Division
1915-1917 Medical and surgical director of the Red Cross hospital of Grand Duke Michael (Southwestern front)
1917-1919 Medical and surgical director for the Red Cross Hospital in Kiev
1918-1919 President of the International Committee to Aid Victims of the Civil War, Kiev
1919-1920 Member of the Provisional Board of the Russian Red Cross and General Secretary of the Committee to Aid Victims of the Civil War
1920 Head of a special mission to the International Committee of the Red Cross in Geneva, Switzerland Medical director of the Russian Red Cross hospital attached to the Russian Embassy in Constantinople, Turkey
1920-1923 Delegate of the Russian Red Cross (old organization) to the International Committee of the Red Cross in Geneva, Switzerland
Scope and Content of Collection
Memoirs, other writings, bulletins, reports, and printed matter relating to medical practice in Russia during World War I, the Russian Revolution and Civil War, efforts to resettle White Russian veterans and refugees after the war, and activities of the International Anticommunist Entente.
Scope and Content of Microfilm Portion of Collection
The materials in the microfilm portion of the collection (originals in Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco) relate mainly to the activities of the director of the Geneva office of the Russian Red Cross (Rossīĭskoe obshchestvo Krasnago kresta), I͡Uriĭ Il'ich Lodyzhenskiĭ papers, in the resettlement of Russian refugees and troops of General P. N. Vrangel's Russian army in the Balkans, 1921-1923.
Also of interest is the file on the defense of Konradi and Polunin, on trial for the assassination of the Soviet ambassador to Switzerland, V. V. Vorovskii, 1923.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials and copyright to them (with some exceptions) are the property of the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
World War, 1914-1918--Medical care.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; International Anticommunist Entente.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Refugees.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Veterans.; Refugees.; Rossīĭskoe obshchestvo Krasnago kresta.; Anti-communist movements.
- "Face au communisme," typescript
  - Volume I (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes two photographic prints attached to first page.
  - Volume II (Box-folder 1: 2)
- "Une carrière médicale mouvementée," photocopy
  - I partie (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - II partie (Box-folder 1: 4)
- "L'œeil qui s'ouvre" (typescript), "L'entrée à l'académie militaire de médicine marque le début d'un nouveau chapitre" (typescript), and "Sur la voie de l'unité chrétienne" (photocopy) (Box-folder 1: 5)
- "Theodore Aubert d'après des souvenirs personnels," photocopy (Box-folder 1: 6)
- Speech, 1952 March 1 (Reel 1)
  Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 1
  Untitled speech on Grand Duke Kirill Vladimirovich, São Paolo, typescript.
- Writings By Others, [1925]-1949
  Arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Artsybashev, M., "Zapiski pisatelia," Za svobodu, printed copy, [1925] (Reel 1)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 2
  - Poliakov, N., "Psalmy," holograph, 1944 (Reel 1)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 3
    Includes author's correspondence with Lodyzhenskii and S. Orloff.
  - S., A., "Die Deutschen in Nordkaukasien (1942-1943)," typescript, undated (Reel 1)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 4
  - Sloskans, Boleslas, "Ma vie de deporte en U.R.S.S.," typescript, 1949 December 14 (Reel 1)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 5
- Subject File, 1921-[1925]
  Materials relating to Russian Red Cross activities abroad and assassination of Soviet diplomat V. V. Vorovskii, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Rossīĭskoe obshchestvo Krasnago kresta
    - Refugees--Soviet Union
      - Office files of the representative of the Russian Red Cross in Geneva relating to resettlement of Russian refugees, mainly in the Balkans
        - 1921 (Reel 1)
          Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 6
        - 1922 January-September (Reel 1)
          Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 7
        - 1922 October-December (Reel 1)
          Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 8
        - 1922 December - 1923 April (Reel 2)
          Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 9
      - Miscellany. Brochures relating to settlement of Russian refugees, 1921-1922 (Reel 2)
        Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 1
    - Miscellany. Charter, bulletins, reports and other printed matter relating to the functioning of the Russian Red Cross abroad, 1921-[1925] (Reel 2)
      Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 2-5
  - Vorovskii, Vatslav Vatslavovich--Assassination, 1923 (Reel 3)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 3: 1-2
    Relates to the trial of Maurice Conradi and Arkadii Polunin in Lausanne, Switzerland.
- Printed Matter, 1922-1939 (Reel 3)
  Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 3: 3
  Includes brochure on famine in Russia (1922), six issues of Rénovation russe (1938-1939), and other materials.